Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn Twitter/FB/IG
@BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I'll let you get some rest.
I have duties to attend to at the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
I'll come visit you again tonight.
But Your Majesty hasn't visited for long...
I have some memorandums to review.
Then don't forget to come tonight, Your Majesty.
I won't.
Take care, Your Majesty.
Coua! Coua!
My Lady! My Lady! What's wrong?
Bring Dr. Xu! Quickly!
Somebody come! Call for Dr. Xu!
Is Consort Oriole all right?
None of the servants at the Palace of Prolonging Happiness
will reveal anything.
We haven't found anything out.
All they said was that Consort Oriole's
troubled sleep affected her prenatal qi,
and that it's not serious.
I do hope so.
I bow before Noble Consort Lumière.
Peace to Your Noble Highness.
Such beautiful flowers.
These are fresh lily blossoms from the gardens.
I picked these especially for Your Noble Highness.
These are called foxtail lilies.
Look at the curling orange stamens,
don't they look just like the tails of foxes?
Best of all, their scent is pleasantly sweet,
and they're easy to cultivate.
In the palace they grow anywhere near water.
Have you sent any to Consort Oriole?
Not yet.
I heard from the Palace of Prolonging Happiness
that Consort Oriole hasn't slept well lately.
Lily flowers are excellent for bringing peace to the mind.
Tell the flower house to send some to Consort Oriole.
Yes, Your Noble Highness.
Your Majesty,
My Lady's pulse is stable now,
and there is no cause for concern.
I will prepare the mugwort for burning now.
Thank you, Dr. Xu.
How did you disturb your prenatal qi?
Your Majesty, I've been upset recently.
I'm afraid this child can't be saved.
Of course it can't!
Your body is no longer fit for pregnancy.
If it weren't for saving your father
and your status in the palace,
I wouldn't have let you force the pregnancy.
I understand, Your Majesty.
If it weren't for Your Majesty's arrangements,
my father wouldn't be free from harm.
But you have yet to do the most important thing.
Noble Consort Lumière has claimed to be unwell,
and refuses to visit me.
I haven't been able to draw a connection
between her and my imminent miscarriage.
Most importantly, anything she sends me
is examined by the imperial doctors,
to confirm nothing is wrong with it.
Opportunities will come if you wait!
I've asked the imperial doctors -
your pregnancy can't last more than 6 months.
If you keep the baby for longer, you may both die.
There is more than one month left,
so think quickly.
I understand, Your Majesty.
The doctor said
not to become overly emotional during this period,
and not to "stay in the same chamber" with His Majesty.
This is to avoid unsettling your prenatal qi, understand?
Yes.
Drink the prenatal tonic.
Dr. Xu will come later to burn mugwort for you.
Remember, do not mention this treatment to anyone.
If anyone asks, you must say your pregnancy is stable.
Yes.
Take care, Your Majesty.
Why are you bringing lilies?
Don't you know My Lady prefers peach blossoms?
The garden house heard that lily blossoms
are the best for calming the mind.
They asked me to pick these for Your Highness's chamber.
Dr. Xu.
Yes.
Please check
if anything is amiss with those lilies.
Certainly.
Your Highness, lily does have a calming effect.
Having lilies in the room
will help Your Highness sleep more restfully.
Then leave them here.
Yes, Your Highness.
Put them here.
Have the lilies been sent?
They have.
The garden house delivers them every day.
The imperial doctor checked the blossoms
and said they are safe.
Consort Oriole also likes them.
Consort Oriole’s birthday is in a few days.
His Majesty will surely pay her a visit.
There is no need for us to be concerned.
Your Highness doesn't need to be concerned about anything.
You can just relax as you feign illness.
If I don’t avoid her,
she would blame me if an accident befalls her.
I can’t afford to let that happen.
Your writing is excellent!
When I was learning to write,
I was much worse than you, Longyue.
I saw my Fourth Brother writing all day.
Even when his hand was trembling, he didn't stop!
Your Fourth Brother works the hardest.
Yes, even His Majesty said so.
He said the Fourth Prince had the latest start
but the greatest aptitude.
It's because you taught him so well.
I heard the imperial court has been advocating
for the eldest prince to become Crown Prince.
The Third Prince is the oldest
and is being raised by the Empress.
Of course he is the center of attention.
But, considering the Third Prince's abilities
he would find it difficult to be a city governor.
How could he be a wise emperor?
True. So His Majesty has pinned his hopes on the Sixth Prince.
The Sixth Prince is still too young to show any potential.
The cleverest is Longyue.
You learn everything with barely any instruction.
The sound of strings and woodwinds has lasted all day.
The Palace of Prolonging Happiness was bustling with joy.
A birthday for a pregnant concubine merits a grand celebration.
I arranged the flowers today with my own hands.
Do they look nice?
Very lovely.
Your Highness is a thousand times more skillful than the servants.
Ask the flower house to send them
to the Palace of Prolonging Happiness
to add festive colors to the occasion.
After delivering the flowers, they should
sprinkle water on the stamens often,
to keep them bright and long-lasting.
Your Majesty.
It's been a busy day.
I can finally relax and
spend time with you, talking,
and having a drink.
Does Your Majesty dislike such hubbub?
I do.
I prefer being alone with you.
You look even bigger now.
It has been five [lunar] months.
The baby will born in another five [lunar] months.
The baby will be as sweet as you are.
You smell wonderful.
Your Majesty, the doctor said
you shouldn't be intimate with me.
It's been five months.
I don't think it will be a problem.
Dr. Xu told me your pregnancy is stable.
But the doctor also said…
Do you not want me to stay with you?
Your Highnesses, terrible news.
Consort Oriole just had a miscarriage!
A miscarriage - why are you so agitated?
Your Noble Highness,
Consort Oriole had a miscarriage because
she and His Majesty were...
It startled His Majesty himself.
Pearl, look after Longyue.
I'm going to the Palace of Prolonging Happiness
with Noble Consort Lumière.
Yes.
My Lady.
So much blood.
What should we do now?
My Lady.
Your Majesties.
Rise quickly and check on Consort Oriole.
Yes.
My Lady.
Take this away, hurry.
- My Lady.
- Take that out.
My lady, please hold on.
- Come here.
- Your Highness.
My child!
How is Consort Oriole?
Her Highness has lost too much blood.
There is no hope of saving the child.
Intense intercourse must be avoided during pregnancy.
Why couldn't Her Highness and His Majesty control themselves?
Besides, Her Highness ...
My Lady, what do we do...
So much blood.
How is she?
There's so much blood.
The imperial doctor said
there's no hope of saving the child.
How could this have happened?
It's my fault.
It was all me.
The child is lost.
Huan Huan,
I've lost another child.
After all these years,
you gave birth to my children,
and Meizhuang gave birth to my child.
I thought Heaven had forgiven me.
But...
But Lingrong's child is lost because of me.
Me.
No, no.
So many princes and princesses have been born,
what could this have to do with Heaven?
What happened today was just an accident.
It wasn't an accident.
I shouldn't have been drinking so late with Lingrong.
I had some wine,
and I was alone with her.
Of course I knew she...
In fact, Consort Oriole had been pregnant for five months.
Didn't the imperial doctors always say the pregnancy was stable?
Even if...
Even if Your Majesty adores Consort Oriole,
it would have been wise to restrain yourself.
I know that too.
But whenever
I'm alone with Consort Oriole,
I can't control myself.
The last few times, I was mindful of her pregnancy,
so nothing occurred.
It might have been the wine I had today...
Your Majesty's mind is still disturbed.
Why not come to my palace to rest?
The imperial doctors will take good care of Consort Oriole.
Consort Oriole's incident is not as important as state affairs.
Your Majesty, please go and rest in Her Majesty's palace.
Indeed.
Consort Oriole has lost this carefully devised round of Go.
Something is amiss with how she miscarried...
The imperial doctors instructed her
not to be intimate with His Majesty.
She knew it, why did she ignore them?
It was His Majesty who did it.
But why was His Majesty so unable to restrain himself?
I've been informed that
His Majesty hasn't been staying at the
Palace of Prolonging Happiness often .
He has mostly been staying with Concubine Paix.
Could Consort Oriole have done this to gain favor?
How stupid!
But I still think the Palace of Eternal Longevity
has something to do with this.
Noble Consort Lumière has claimed to be unwell,
and kept her hands clean of any involvement.
Does Your Majesty wish to thoroughly investigate?
We can't.
If this matter is investigated,
people may find out Consort Oriole's pregnancy
was unstable from the start.
It might expose our involvement with Dr. Xu.
In that case, His Majesty will not only lose his pity for Consort Oriole
but we will be implicated as well.
So we can't do anything but let this go.
Such a pity that we couldn't use this pregnancy
to defeat Noble Consort Lumière.
There's no rush, Your Majesty.
Even without Consort Oriole, there are new concubines.
If Consort Oriole is clever enough,
then she knows how to use a man's pity and sympathy
to secure her footing in the harem.
Your Majesty, have some pastry.
I have no appetite.
Since Consort Oriole's accident,
Your Majesty has been so dispirited.
Your Majesty must take care of your "dragon's body".
How's Consort Oriole?
The same.
She doesn't want to see or talk to anyone.
Your Majesty.
Attendant Kang is here to pay her respects.
Let her in.
Yes.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Noble Consort Lumiere.
Rise.
I heard that Your Majesty has had a poor appetite.
I ordered these peach flower cookies
to be made for Your Majesty.
Leave them here.
Your headpiece...
Have you no heart?
A child has just been lost in the palace
and Consort Oriole is still sick.
Who did you fix yourself up for?
Forgive me Your Majesty, I...
Take your things and get out!
Your Majesty, please allow your anger to calm.
I have done many things against my will,
under many circumstances out of my control.
For the stability of the Great Qing,
I have killed many.
But this time...
My Lady, you're up.
The imperial doctor has instructed you to
avoid the wind because of your weak constitution.
Did he?
I don't feel weak or cold.
My Lady,
His Majesty has rewarded your father generously.
Is that consolation or compensation?
Because I'll never be a mother for the rest of my days.
In fact... from the very start, this child
could not have been saved.
I knew this day would come, sooner or later.
Whether myself or this child,
we were merely pawns in someone else's game.
There was no way we'd be saved, in the end.
My Lady, please don't be so sad.
His Majesty does care about you, after all.
Coua, do you know
I feel so exhausted?
Like never before.
Yet I know,
once my body has recovered,
I'll again be subjected to a puppeteer's manipulation
in this never-ending fight in the harem.
But Coua,
I feel like I'm down to my last breath.
I've no strength left in me to fight.
My Lady, you are overcome with sadness.
You may leave now.
Zhen Huan,
I broke your trust.
Karma never fails.
And it has caught up with me.
Your Majesty,
do you like the aroma of the incense I put on?
It's subtle, and calming to the mind.
I only acquired it recently.
I've been eager to bring it for Your Majesty to try.
Speaking of incense,
no one is as skilled as Consort Oriole.
Of course.
Auspice,
present it to Her Majesty.
Yes.
This Condensed Dew incense from
Consort Oriole's palace is a real treasure.
It's as refreshing as a garden of flowers.
Don’t underestimate its value by its size.
If someone in the harem got their hands
on even a tiny sliver of this,
they would be able to keep His Majesty's heart.
What on earth is this?
Your Majesty,
sensual desires can be stimulated
not only
through affection, but also with herbs.
Did you really obtain this incense from Consort Oriole?
Your Majesty is aware
that I have no reason to frame Consort Oriole.
Is it poisonous?
It's not.
Perhaps Consort Oriole was being foolish
and wanted to keep His Majesty by her side.
Since the day of Consort Oriole's miscarriage,
my suspicion has grown.
His Majesty can hold his liquor.
How could he lose control of himself after a few drinks?
Knowing that Consort Oriole was pregnant,
even if His Majesty wanted to perform "Zhou Gong's ritual,"
he wouldn't have been so impetuous as to
lose sight of the most important priority.
Why didn't Consort Oriole herself stop it?
Did she not care about her pregnancy?
So I sent someone to investigate,
and found this in the ashes of incense
discarded by Coua.
I checked the records from the Household Department.
Before Consort Oriole's birthday,
His Majesty either worked in the Hall of Mental Cultivation
or spent the night in Concubine Paix's palace.
He rarely visited the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
Is it possible
Consort Oriole made this foolish decision
to compete for favor,
thinking her prenatal qi was stable after five months?
Imperial Noble Consort,
could there be any misunderstanding?
Consort Oriole wouldn't be so bold
as to trifle with an imperial heir.
Did someone plot this against hert?
Noble Consort Lumière's theory is not unfounded.
Auspice, explain further.
Yes.
I was investigating at Her Imperial Highness's behest.
I saw that a censer was tipped over but still burning
in the backyard of the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
This was found in the ashes.
I confirmed with the imperial doctors
and then the servants in the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
They said all the spices were kept by Consort Oriole herself.
I went looking inside the palace chambers when unguarded.
Some important boxes were locked
and couldn't be accessed without keys.
Continue.
Under the orders of Her Imperial Highness,
I retrieved all the boxes containing spices,
one of which contained exactly the same incense
as what was just presented.
Besides, the locked boxes were placed on high shelves.
The maids said that
Consort Oriole hadn't planned to use them recently,
but for some reason she did.
What else could it be for?
How despicable of her to compete for favor in this way,
causing the loss of an imperial heir!
Your Highness, don't worry.
We're just doing a search of your palace.
A search?
More like the raiding of a criminal.
I know the Palace of Eternal Longevity has been searched before.
"Fortune goes around like winds and waters."
Now it's my palace.
"Fortunes do go around."
When the good days end,
the bad ones begin.
Whether days are good or bad
is not to be dictated by a eunuch.
Sir, I found it.
A eunuch is still a person.
We have a voice like any person.
Very well, Consort Oriole.
To the Hall of Mental Cultivation, please.
For her use of devious tricks in the palace,
what does Your Majesty think should be her punishment?
I've ordered her palace to be searched.
She has just lost a child, after all.
How about removing her honorary name and demoting her to Companion?
I believe Consort Oriole has already
learned her lesson from losing her child.
That's enough for her.
But how dare she use those foul spices to beguile His Majesty
and debauch the harem?
She cannot be spared.
Although Consort Oriole is guilty of concocting stimulating incense,
she has lost her child and her fertility.
She did learn a lesson.
Would Your Majesty spare her this time?
Besides, there have been benefits
from her ability to combine herbs.
Back when my face was scratched by the cat,
Consort Oriole gave me this Scar Relief Gel.
The scar disappeared soon after I applied the gel -
not even a trace is left.
Your Majesty, please consider her past merits
and forgive her this time.
If I recall correctly, Noble Consort Lumière,
you were scratched during your first pregnancy?
Yes.
Why would Your Imperial Highness ask?
Your Majesty,
I've always had a weak constitution and
never had Heaven's blessing of pregnancy.
What Noble Consort Lumière mentioned just now
reminded me that
she was healthy and strong back then -
even though Nian Shilan was harsh on her,
why would she have miscarried after kneeling for just an hour?
Thinking back on it, doesn't it seem odd?
A healthy body cannot sustain a stab in the back.
Where's Wei Lin?
He's waiting outside the hall
for Your Majesty's routine pulse check.
Send him in.
Wei Lin is summoned.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Take a look at this Scar Relief Gel
and see if there's anything amiss.
Aye.
This salve contains an unusually high level of musk.
If this was applied to the face every day
one would miscarry within three months.
How could this be?
It was Lingrong who killed my child.
Without a doubt.
The ointment has dried up.
I can see that Your Highness hasn't used it for a long time.
It would have taken at least two jars of it to remove the scars.
Such a dosage would guarantee a miscarriage.
Your Majesty ... Your Majesty.
What a cruel heart Lingrong has!
She was so merciless, even to her sister of many years.
Her plan was watertight!
"Human hearts are most unpredictable."
It was also An Lingrong's maid who went to Shen Meizhuang
and disrupted her pregnancy.
Now we know that she's harbored these unbelievable intentions
The maid must have done that at her orders.
Poor Princess Jinghe lost her mother at birth.
When An Lingrong looks at the princess,
I wonder what she feels?
Very well.
The woman I've favored for so many years
is unfit to be a human.
Your Majesty,
we found something in Consort Oriole's palace.
These musk glands have a strong odor
and the quality is extremely rare.
They would have an extremely powerful effect.
I can't imagine how many died because of them.
Take them away immediately.
Your Majesty,
I have brought Consort Oriole here.
She's waiting outside the hall.
Your Highness, Consort Oriole,
His Majesty has requested that you go in.
Such beautiful sunshine...
won't be mine to see anymore.
Consort Lumiere's miscarriage,
and the death of Shen Meizhuang -
was it all your doing?
Ever since I committed myself to my actions,
I have long expected this day.
Consort Oriole,
you've been by my side for many years
and have never disobeyed me.
How could you have been so vicious
behind my back?
I don't like the name Consort Oriole.
I am no more than a bird you feed.
Your Majesty,
you've never had the slightest affection for me.
Do you treat me any differently
than an obedient dog or cat?
And as for being vicious,
deep behind the harem gates, who hasn't been vicious?
Did anyone give instructions to you?
Anything you want to explain?
Everything is my own fault.
May Your Majesty please grant my punishment.
Anyone can have moments of cruelty.
Because in the palace,
everyone can feel constrained and powerless.
But you, however,
have been a hundred times more vicious than others.
I won't grant you death.
Instead, I will even keep your honorary title.
The Palace of Prolonging Happiness will be your Cold Palace.
When your health is restored,
I will command that you be slapped every day.
You will kneel in front of the Buddha
and repent for your sins every single day.
With you as an example,
I challenge anyone in the palace to follow suit.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Take her away.
Confine her to the Palace of Prolonging Happiness.
No one is to attend to her.
As for any servants she's had,
the ones close to her will be flogged to death
and the others sold off as slaves.
They will be banished from the capital for life.
I want to see her destroy herself.
Killing her would only soil the hands of others.
This stick of incense
is for my unborn child.
May his soul rest in peace in Heaven.
Look at the color of the stamens.
It looks just like the Seduction Incense.
Yes...
The incense which Xiao-Yunzi discovered by chance
became the critical tool enabling us to defeat An Lingrong.
The garden house brought foxtail lilies every day.
Who would expect that a bit of moist incense powder
would have been sprinkled onto the lily stamens that night?
An Lingrong has always been outstanding at making incense.
But now the ash from that incense drifts over her grave.
Su Peisheng has said
he will make sure her palace is well cared for.
Make sure she doesn't die.
Su Peisheng knows what's proper.
Your Highness need not worry.
His Majesty has ordered An Bihuai's execution
with no delay.
It's today or tomorrow.
Inform her at an appropriate time.
She's his daughter after all,
and will want to cry and grieve.
Yes.
Your Highness, Mr. Su is here.
Peace to Noble Consort Lumière.
Mr. Su.
Your Highness, Consort Oriole would like to see you.
Just as well.
There are things I'd like to ask her personally.
Let's be quiet, Mr. Su.
Don't draw any attention.
Your Highness need not worry, I will take care of it.
One more thing.
Consort Oriole said she wanted to eat some bitter almonds.
His Majesty has said
her needs will be granted.
She will remain as Consort Oriole.
My sister, you're here.
Look at me.
Haven't I aged so much?
Do I still look the same as before?
Lingrong, you look just the same,
but your heart is not as pure.
If I remained as innocent as I was,
I might have died a thousand times in this harem.
Do you know who taught me embroidery?
My mother.
She was a weaver in Suzhou.
My father liked her very much.
That year,
my father was only a spice trader, of no repute.
My mother bought him a low-ranking official post,
by selling her embroidery.
She damaged her eyesight
by doing needlework for him,
and her beauty declined too.
So my father married many concubines.
Although my mother was the primary wife,
she had neither beauty nor a calculating mind.
She was always at a disadvantage.
In the end, my father didn't even want to see her.
After I entered the harem,
Consort Fleur was savage,
and the Empress was deeply cunning.
Even the maids dared to bully me.
I was afraid.
Every night I had the same dream -
that I'd end up just like my mother,
blind, bullied, and living a life worse than death.
Everyone knows how hard our days in the palace are.
But no matter how hard life is,
and how much one has to scheme,
you shouldn't have hurt those close to you,
especially those who saw you as their own sister.
I used to...
believe that you treated me with a sincere heart.
You had everything -
Noble birth,
a beautiful face,
and His Majesty's affection.
But me - all I received from others was coldness.
I even had to suffer Consort Fleur's humiliation
because you gained His Majesty's favor.
Later, I knew that
your kindness to me,
your caring and thoughtful help
was merely like giving cold leftover rice as charity.
When Shen Meizhuang was confined,
you wanted me to compete for favor
to strengthen your own position.
The three of us leaned on each other
when we entered the harem.
I would never have forced you to do anything against your will.
At that time, Meizhuang was confined.
If you and I hadn't joined hands,
we would have been like a
"fish between the knife and chopping board."
The bitter almonds do taste good.
After a long time in the harem,
even bitter almonds taste sweet.
Don't hate me.
Don't call me ruthless.
To be honest,
I just couldn't reconcile myself with my fate -
to be someone else's stepping stone,
without ever being heard;
to live out my life without making a sound.
I had to compete for favor.
I couldn't avoid resenting Her Majesty, and His Majesty,
and anyone who used me as their pawn
and treated me like a toy.
Of course, I knew the Empress never truly wanted to help me.
Of course I knew...
His Majesty never really loved me.
But how can one expect
a sincere heart in this harem?
After everything,
I resent you the most.
Because you have everything now,
and as the end nears,
I'm left with nothing.
If you haven't completely betrayed your conscience...
look back and ask yourself - how many did you harm?
I refuse to look back.
The nights in the harem - so cold and long.
I dare not recall...
how I survived every single second.
No matter how cold,
you shouldn't have used another's blood
to keep yourself warm.
To keep warm?
My sister...
you and I are lifelong enemies, regardless.
Enemies?
I won't hate you,
nor will I forgive you.
Because you are unworthy.
Yes.
My whole life...
has been worthless from the start.
The Empress...
Killed by the Empress!
I'm sorry.
You were promised a peaceful life...
But I ended up ruining it.
This life ...
and this breath ...
(Lotuses are harvested south of River Yangtze.)
was never mine to control.
But on this day,
(How endlessly their verdant canopy expands)
I can finally take life...
(There’s a pair of koi fish frolicking through jade waves.)
into my own hands.
(They swim to the east; They swim to the south.)
That rosy dawn reminds me of the morning we were selected for the harem.
But the minds of the people seeing it
are no longer the same.
(Who’s the girl deep in the lotus leaves?)
Your Highness was inside for a long time.
What did Consort Oriole say to you?
(She tossed a flower pod and smiled.)
Nothing.
She is truly pitiful.
(She tossed a flower pod and smiled.)
Her Highness Consort Oriole has died.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.